<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<Root><_1_story>clown party Hundreds show up to Portland clown march, in silly day of joyous protest “We will keep finding ridiculous ways to disrupt the status quo,” said Raggs, the lead clown. Lillian Mongeau Hughes    The Oregonian/OregonLive When President Donald Trump got reelected in 2024, JoJo Ruby was not pleased. “I was feeling really isolated and lonely and unsure where my place in the revolution was as a clown,” she said. Then she thought, as revolutionaries so often do: “I think I need to start a parade.” Ruby’s dream became a reality last April when she organized for hundreds of clowns to take over Southeast Hawthorne Boulevard. They marched with signs carrying defiant messages like, “Don’t read this sign!” Speaking to The Oregonian/OregonLive from the center of the second annual clown festival in the moments before marching, Ruby, 34, said the movement has grown steadily ever since. There are now clown picnics in Laurelhurst Park every first Sunday of the month and a clown bike ride — organized with the World Naked Bike Ride team — is planned for August. All of it is in protest of Trump, in general, she said, and the federal immigration crackdown, specifically. “We’re clorganizing,” said Ruby, whose clown name is Raggs. “All clowns welcome.”  Anyone who is not a clown, or doesn’t think they are, can come too, Ruby said. A quick stop through the clownification tent would do the trick. Most of the couple hundred people at the clown party on Saturday said they were already clowns when they arrived, though there was a distinct variation in the level of planning that seemed to have gone into the various costumes. Two men were spotted in regular old jeans and tees topped off with curly rainbow wigs. Several people who looked primarily like moms watching small children, wore red noses. Others had gone all out. Summer Robinson and Phoenix Butterfield, both 11, had carefully sourced their costumes from hand-me-downs, Amazon and Temu. “I kind of want to go with, like, the abandoned circus clown look,” said Summer, who was wearing at least five rainbow-colored items, including an amazingly bright tie-dye shirt. Phoenix said she preferred the black-and-white clown style often associated with traditional Harlequin clowns out of 16th century Italy. For a modern touch she’d added some horror elements, including fake blood dripping down her front.  “It’s a person’s choice,” Phoenix said when asked what makes someone a clown. “It can be anything — funny, scary, sad.” Hugo Gustafson, 18, a graphic design student at Portland State University had gone the funny route. He was decked out in full face paint, a striped shirt of many colors and what looked like workman’s pants, complete with a hammer loop, but in multicolored patches. “We have a bit of generational talent that comes with it,” he said of his family’s longstanding clowning traditions. Did he have a clown talent? “Oh yeah!” Gustafson ran to grab his unicycle. His friend, Solomon Sledge, 18, was far more sedate in his clowniness, as befits a young man majoring in engineering. But his enthusiasm for the day was just as colorful as Gustafson’s pants. “Really, the attitude makes you a clown,” Sledge said. “If you’re down to be silly, down to have a fun time … being extroverted, being jumpy, being bouncy — I think those things make you a really good clown.” Bimby Balloona, also known as Ariann Ramsy from Bend, had shown up with a pink pole. She spun around the pole in a way that made it look like she was walking on air, then she turned upside down while continuing to spin. She let others try out the pole themselves, leading to a steady stream of less accomplished, but just as joyful, pole dancers. Ramsy, 24, said she was there with her friend, Becky, for similar reasons.  “The world needs a little more joy out there, so I’m here to help spread a little bit of it,” Ramsy said. “Whimsy and being in touch with your inner child is all it takes to be a clown.” Becky, a sock puppet, just squeaked, presumably in agreement. Patrick Connell, 49, was in town from his home in Massachusetts. He was visiting friends who lived in Lake Oswego and said he’d never really planned to be a clown, he’d had clowning thrust upon him. “I was born with huge feet and forced to wear clown shoes,” he said. “I just went with it.” Standing before the crowd just before they headed out of Laurelhurst Park, Ruby said it would not be the last march of the clowns. “We will keep finding ridiculous ways to disrupt the status quo,” she said to cheers, clapping and the high-pitched buzz of many kazoos. Anyone wanting to attend the next clowntastic event can follow @theaprilfools on Instagram for more information.</_1_story><_1_img1 href="file://images/XQXIIGDQGNEQNNXHV254DGKN2A_Advance_CMYK.jpg"></_1_img1><_2_story>Native history Thousands of artifacts to be returned to Umatilla Indian Reservation The Confederated Tribes of the Umatilla Indian Reservation signed an agreement in late March to acquire Fred L. Mitchell’s collection of beaded bags and other historical items. Matthew Kish   The Oregonian/OregonLive Hundreds of beaded bags and pouches are among the thousands of historic items that will be returned to the Umatilla Indian Reservation. On March 31, the Confederated Tribes of the Umatilla Indian Reservation signed an agreement to acquire Fred L. Mitchell’s collection of tribal artwork and artifacts.  Mitchell owned “the finest collection of twentieth-century Columbia River Plateau beadwork in existence,” Steve Grafe wrote in “Plateau Pictorial Beadwork: The Fred L. Mitchell Collection.”  Mitchell is a retired firefighter and former mayor of Walla Walla. He started collecting artifacts when he was 5, according to the Confederated Umatilla Journal. His collection grew to include cradleboards, gauntlets, horse-trappings, cornhusk bags, huckleberry baskets, photographs and tools.  The agreement includes 15,000 “ancient stone and metal items,” according to OPB, as well as over 800 beaded bags and pouches, more than 1,250 historic photographs, 70 pairs of beaded gauntlets, 50 beaded dresses and 15 cradleboards. The items will be displayed at the Tamástslikt Cultural Institute in Pendleton on the Umatilla Indian Reservation. The collection “dramatically” expands the museum’s collection, the institute said in a press release.  A ceremonial blanket was draped over Mitchell’s shoulders at the signing ceremony at the Nixyáawii Governance Center.  “We are so grateful that every time Fred saw something that was exquisite, that was the finest of its kind, he kept it for us,” Tamástslikt Cultural Institute Director Bobbie Conner said at the ceremony, according to OPB. “He didn’t know it was coming here then, but he’s been taking care of these goods, many of them, for more than seven decades, and we are so proud of that.” The Roundhouse Foundation, a private family foundation that supports rural Oregon, is among the donors that helped fund the acquisition. The Confederated Tribes of the Umatilla Indian Reservation includes the Cayuse, Walla Walla and Umatilla Tribes. </_2_story><_2_img1 href="file://images/FDAML3VDIRFKVAU2BOKQFSQB34_Advance_CMYK.jpg"></_2_img1><_3_img1 href="file://images/XJCQA5J2ANBQBCHC53LUHEWEKQ_Advance_CMYK.jpg"></_3_img1><_3_story>Baird’s beaked whale washes up on Long Beach Peninsula The whale was too decomposed for researchers to determine a cause of death.  Matthew Kish   The Oregonian/OregonLive Researchers who examined a Baird’s beaked whale that washed up in Southwest Washington could not find an obvious cause of death.  A team from Portland State University examined the whale carcass but it was too decomposed to conduct a necropsy, said Michael Milstein, a spokesperson for the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, in an email. The whale was found Friday on the Long Beach Peninsula, according to OPB. At least 19 whales have washed up on the West Coast this year, according to the news organization.  Milstein said NOAA was also aware of a roughly 40-foot adult male gray whale that had washed up near the Ocean Shores area of Washington. He said there was no obvious cause of death and the whale appeared malnourished, but not as emaciated as others.  The recent necropsy of a juvenile humpback whale that washed ashore near Yachats in November found evidence of spinal cord disease likely caused by an infection. Crabbing gear had also appeared to entangle the whale. Baird’s beaked whales “rarely” strand in Oregon, Milstein said, adding they “tend to remain in more distant waters, diving deep for long periods.” The species can weigh more than 13 tons. The carcass will likely be left to decompose naturally.</_3_story></Root>
